<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1250" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl" ?>
<content lang="en" id="status">
    <h1>Current Status</h1>
    <p>
        While Sooda is quite a new technology, it's already been given some serious testing.
        It is currently used as a Data Access Layer technology for Atmo - 
        a workflow-building technology created by the <a href="http://www.atm.com.pl/">company I work for</a> and
        has been deployed in a number of projects.
    </p>
    <p>
        The following tables summarize the current status of Sooda. Some areas obviously need more
        serious testing before they can be called production-ready. I don't have time or equipment to do all the 
        testing myself, so If you'd like to help us improve Sooda
        by providing testing and support for one of the following areas, join the <link href="development">development</link> team.
    </p>
    <p>
        Platform support:
    </p>
    <p>
        <div class="table">
            <table>
                <col width="30%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="20%" />
                <col width="40%" />
            <tr>
                <th>CLI</th>
                <th>Supported</th>
                <th>Tested</th>
                <th>Comments</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>.NET 1.0</td>
                <td>no</td>
                <td></td>
                <td>It's not recommended to use Sooda with .NET 1.0. It may not even compile on this platform. Use .NET 1.1 instead</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>.NET 1.1</td>
                <td>yes</td>
                <td>well tested</td>
                <td>this is the primary development environment of Sooda</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>.NET 2.0</td>
                <td>partially</td>
                <td>untested</td>
                <td>.NET 2.0-specific features like partial classes and nullable types aren't supported yet. Otherwise
                    everything should work unmodified on .NET 2.0 (modulo some warnings during the compilation)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mono 1.x</td>
                <td>partially</td>
                <td>partially tested</td>
                <td>unit tests mostly pass, due to some limitations of the platform some features (in particular separate stub compilation)
                    aren't supported and <a href="http://bugzilla.ximian.com/show_bug.cgi?id=52813">will probably never be</a>.</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </div>
    </p>
    <p>
        Database support:
    </p>
    <p>
        <div class="table">
        <table>
                <col width="30%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="20%" />
                <col width="40%" />
            <tr>
                <th>RDBMS</th>
                <th>Supported</th>
                <th>Tested</th>
                <th>Comments</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>MS SQL Server 2000</td>
                <td>yes</td>
                <td>well tested</td>
                <td>this is the main RDBMS we use while developing Sooda</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>PostgreSQL 7.1.x</td>
                <td>yes</td>
                <td>untested</td>
                <td>some basic features tested on Linux/Mono with Npgsql driver</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>PostgreSQL 8.x</td>
                <td>yes</td>
                <td>untested</td>
                <td>basic features tested on Windows with Npgsql driver</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Oracle</td>
                <td>perhaps</td>
                <td>untested</td>
                <td>there's support for Oracle join syntax, completely untested</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>MySQL 3.xx</td>
                <td>partially</td>
                <td>untested</td>
                <td>trivial things (insert, update, delete) should work, in complex SOQL queries Sooda relies 
                    on subqueries and they aren't supported in MySQL3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>MySQL 4.xx</td>
                <td>yes</td>
                <td>untested</td>
                <td>basic features tested on Linux/Mono with ByteFX driver</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </div>
    </p>
</content>

